RG 021, Department of Mental Health and Addiction Services
Connecticut State Library
Department of Mental Health and Addiction Services records
1866-1996
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Dept. of Mental Health and Addiction Services
998.5 cubic feet (includes subgroups)
The Department of Mental Health and Addiction Services (DMHAS) promotes and administers comprehensive, recovery-oriented services in the areas of mental health treatment and substance abuse prevention and treatment throughout Connecticut.
RG021
Multiple
Historical Note
The Department of Mental Health was established on October 1, 1953. It succeeded the Joint Committee of State Mental Hospitals comprising representatives from the Boards of Trustees of the State Mental Hospitals: the first at Middletown in 1867, called Connecticut Hospital for the Insane, now known as Connecticut Valley Hospital (CVH); the next, in 1904, Norwich State Hospital; the third, beginning in 1933, Fairfield Hills State Hospital, and finally in 1953, Connecticut Child Study and Treatment Home. Norwich State Hospital and Fairfield Hills were closed down. The Department of Mental Health combined the State Mental Hospitals into one department. In 1975, children's psychiatric services was transferred from the Department of Mental Health to the Department of Children and Youth Services, which was later called the Department of Children and Families (DCF). On July 1, 1995, the Department of Mental Health was absorbed into the Department of Mental Health and Addiction Services from the former Department of Public Health and Addiction Services. This is the “single state agency for providing comprehensive mental health and substance abuse services throughout Connecticut.”
See also the.
Scope and Content
Contains records relating to Connecticut State Hospital for the Insane/Connecticut Valley Hospital; Division of Alcohol and Drug Dependence Division; Commission on Alcoholism; Associate Commissioner. Child and Adolescent; Joint Board of Mental Health; Council of Mental Health; Fairfield Hills Hospital; Norwich State Hospital; Commissioner's files. Connecticut State Hospital for the Insane/Connecticut Valley Hospital contain superintendents files, 1867-1960; trustees minutes, 1866-1961; fiscal files, 1889-1943; Personnel records, 1874-1941; patient files, 1916-1965; medical staff records, 1901-1951; school of nursing records, 1904-1939; miscellaneous material, 1889-1976; and manual for practical nursing procedures, 1928.
Arrangement
Series 1. Connecticut Valley Hospital/Connecticut State Hospital for the Insane, 1866-1991
Series 2. Alcohol and Drug Dependence Division, 1956-1979, 22 cubic feet
Accession: 1983-022, Subject and grant files, circa 1956-1979, 3 cubic feet
Accession: 1983-022, State Advisory Board minutes, 1962-1975, 1 folder
Accession: 2005-020, Community in-service centers, 1959-1979, 19 cubic feet
Series 3. Commission on Alcoholism, 1945-1959, Accession: 1983-022, 0.50 cubic feet
Series 4. Associate Commissioner. Child and Adolescent, 1964-1976, Accession: 1987-031, 3 cubic feet
Series 5. Joint Board of Mental Health, 1948-1951, Accession: T000947, 2 folders
Series 6. Council of Mental Health, 1952-1957, Accession: T000947, 0.75 cubic feet (8 folders)
Subgroup 7. Fairfield Hills Hospital, 1933-1995
Subgroup 8. Norwich State Hospital, 1904-1996
Series 9. Commissioner's files, 1958-1994, Accession: 2003-035, 17 cubic feet
Related Material
None.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. Dept. of Mental Health; Connecticut. Dept. of Mental Health and Addiction Services
Subjects:
Connecticut. Dept. of Mental Health and Addiction Services -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut. Dept. of Mental Health -- Records and correspondence; Mental health -- Connecticut; Mental health services -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Correspondence; Medical records; Minutes; Reports; Personnel records; Scrapbooks; Speeches
Restrictions on Access
New Exemption: Public Act 11-242, section 37 amends subsection (b) (10) of Conn. Gen. Stat. sec. 1-210 and adds to the exemptions of the Freedom of Information Act any records created as a result of a doctor-patient or a therapist-patient relationship. This closure applies to all records listed below as Restricted.
Patients: Files continue to be made available to patients themselves upon reliable proof of identification which may be a current copy of a Connecticut driver's license with a photograph or current credit card with the patient's name on it.
Families: Section 52-146c of the Connecticut General Statutes allows "next of kin" the right to view records of a deceased patient who was also a relative.
Relatives of deceased patients should contact Assistant State Archivist Allen Ramsey by email at allen.ramsey@ct.gov or send a letter with the following information:
- Full name of the patient.
- Approximate years patient was treated at the hospital.
- Name, e-mail, and telephone of the requestor.
The State Archives will search for the folder and will report the results of the search to the requestor. If a file is found and the requestor wants to view or receive copies of the file, the following information must first be presented to the State Archivist:
- Proof of identity through a copy of a current Connecticut driver's license with a photograph or a copy of a current credit card with the requestor's name on it.
- Proof that the patient is deceased through a copy of a death certificate or obituary.
- Proof that the requestor is a "next of kin" to the deceased patient through a copy of a birth certificate, obituary with the name of the requestor mentioned as a survivor, or a signed and dated notarized statement of relationship to the patient.
Other Parties: According to the new exemption, medical records are closed to other parties.
Record Series Listed Below: Records listed below labeled as non-restricted or unrestricted are open to all researchers who have read the rules of use and signed the registration forms. Since these records are stored off site, they may not be available on the same day.
See the policy.
Container List
- Subgroup 1. Connecticut State Hospital for the Insane/Connecticut Valley Hospital, 1866-1976; 223 cubic feet
  Trustee minutes, superintendents files, nursing records, surgical records, legal opinions hearings, patient records, 1962-65, and various other records pertaining to the operation of the Connecticut Valley Hospital. The State Archives only has a sampling of files.
  RG 021:001, Connecticut Valley Hospital Inventory of Records
- Series 2. Alcohol and Drug Dependence Division, 1956-1979; 22 cubic feet
  - Subject and Grant Files, circa 1956-1979; 1983-022; 3 cubic feet
    UNRESTRICTED
    - Grant Summaries - ADDD, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Grant Applications - ADDD, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Grant Review Committee, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Minutes - RFP Review Committee Meeting, 1974 December 31 - 1975 January 7 (Box 1)
    - DARTEC Educational Grant (Box 1)
    - Legislative Program Review Committee (Box 1)
    - RFP Information (Box 1)
    - Staffing Grants (Box 1)
    - Federal Grant #5-H19-MH-17837-001 Year (Box 1)
    - Federal Grant #5-H19-MH-17837-002, Continuation Year (Box 1)
    - Federal Grant #5-H19-MH-17837-03 (Box 1)
    - Federal Grant #5-H19-MH-17837-04, 4th Year Staffing Grant (Box 1)
    - Federal Grant #5-H19-MH-17837-005, 5th Year Staffing Grant (Box 1)
    - Narcotics Addicts Treatment Facility (Box 1)
    - Research Grants - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Community Based Treatment Program (Box 2)
    - Adolescents Grant (Box 2)
    - Fullway House Rehabilitation Program (Box 2)
    - State Occupational Alcoholism Program (Box 2)
    - Niantic Project (Box 2)
    - Compass Club (Box 2)
    - COA Evaluation Project (Box 2)
    - NARA Title I, II, III (Box 2)
    - NARA II (Box 2)
    - PPBS (Box 3)
    - DARTEC (Box 3)
    - Alcohol and Drug Addiction Control (Box 3)
    - Community Service Center (Box 3)
    - ADRU (Box 3)
    - University of Connecticut, Health Center, Dept. of Pediatrics (Box 3)
    - Training Center - UCONN Agreement (Box 3)
    - Occupational Alcoholism Program (Box 3)
    - Government Employees Programs (Box 3)
    - EEA Reports (Box 3)
    - Proposed Employees' Assistance Program (Box 3)
    - Reports: By ADDD - Reports #1-9 (Box 3)
    - List of Operating Treatment and Evaluation Programs (Box 3)
    - Reports: By ADDD - Reports #10-14 (Box 3)
    - Reports: Annual Report of Dept. of Mental Health (Box 4)
    - Annual Report by the COA to the Governor, 1952-1953 (Box 4)
    - Reports - By COA: Manual of Operations, 1957 (Box 4)
    - Reports: By State Alcohol Council: Therapeutic Shelters as Entry Point for the Care System (Box 4)
    - Reports by Alcohol and Drug Abuse Council - Minimum Stds for Treatment Programs (Box 4)
    - Annual Reports by Other Depts. of State Government, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
    - Reports: Proposal - NIDA 271-76-2213, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Technical Reports #1-3 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Technical Reports #4-6 (Box 4)
    - NE Regional Support Center, Bimonthly Report, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Patient Fate - McCarthy Report (Box 5)
    - Functions of the Division Advisory Council (Box 5)
    - Statutes of Connecticut Pertaining to the COA (Box 5)
    - Fee Policy - Outpatient Clinics (Box 5)
    - Proposed Plan on Alcoholism and Drug Addiction (Box 5)
    - By Laws - Governing Authority, Dept. of Mental Health (Box 5)
    - Outpatient Alcohol Detoxification (Box 5)
    - Suggested Allocation of Funds (Box 5)
    - 1976 Connecticut Plan for Alcoholism Treatment and Prevention (Box 5)
    - Testimony Before Legislative Committee (Box 5)
    - NE Regional Support Center - Conference, 1976 November (Box 5)
    - Symposium: Institute for Single State Agency Management, 1976 December (Box 5)
    - Alcohol Problems and Alcohol Policy (Box 5)
    - CODAP 3 Training Session (Box 6)
    - Training Center (Box 6)
    - Personnel - ADD Counselor Job Description (Box 6)
    - Request for Approval of Position (Box 6)
    - Mental Health Dept. Personnel System (Box 6)
    - Personnel - Old Pay Plans (Box 6)
    - Personnel - Photographs (Box 6)
    - Letters and Special Reports - State (Box 6)
    - COA Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Newsletter: Connecticut Mental Health Reporter (Box 6)
  - State Advisory Board Minutes, 1962-1975; 1983-022; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Community In-Service Centers, 1959-1979; 2005-020; 19 cubic feet
    RESTRICTED
    - Blue Hills Hospital - Inpatient Record, 1959-1979
      - Compass Club Members
        - AB-DU, 1960-1979 (Box 1)
        - EN-KR, 1960-1979 (Box 2)
        - LA-NU, 1960-1979 (Box 3)
        - OB-SL, 1959-1979 (Box 4)
        - SM-ZA, 1960-1979 (Box 5)
        - Evaluation Group, H-O (Box 6)
        - Second Admission, A-B (Box 7)
        - A-F, 1960-1964 (Box 8)
        - I-L (Box 9)
        - G-I (Box 10)
        - SU-Z (Box 11)
        - C-DO (Box 12)
        - MC-P, 1964-1971 (Box 13)
      - Cadres House
        - S-T (Box 14)
        - S-Z, before 1977 (Box 15)
        - M-R (Box 16)
        - B-Y (Box 17)
        - A-F (Box 18)
        - A-M (Box 19)
- Series 3. Commission on Alcoholism, 1945-1959; 1983-022; 0.50 cubic feet
  - Board of Trustees Official Minutes, 1945-1959 (Box 7)
- Series 4. Associate Commissioner. Child and Adolescent, circa 1964-1976; 1987-031; 3 cubic feet
  Consolidation of state children's services
  Unprocessed
  - Charles Launi (Box 1-3)
- Series 5. Joint Board of Mental Health, 1948-1951; T000947; 2 folders
  Monthly Reports and Papers
  - 1948-1951, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Series 6. Council of Mental Health, 1952-1957; T000947; 0.75 cubic feet (8 folders)
  Papers
  - 1952-1955, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - 1956-1957, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Subgroup 7. Fairfield Hills Hospital, 1933-1995
  RG 021:007, Fairfield Hills Hospital Inventory of Records
- Subgroup 8. Norwich State Hospital, 1904-1996
  RG 021:008, Norwich State Hospital Inventory of Records
- Series 9. Commissioner's Files, 1958-1994; 2003-035; 17 cubic feet
  - Awards, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
  - Department of Administrative Services (Box 1)
  - Affirmative Action (Box 1)
  - APT Foundation, 1986-1989 (Box 1)
  - Agreements, 1984-1990 (Box 1)
  - Block Grant Applications, 1987-1990 (Box 1)
  - Bond Authorizations, 1987-1990 (Box 1)
  - CADAC Correspondence, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
  - CADAC Plan Task Force, Vol. I (Box 1)
  - CADAC Plan Task Force, Vol. II (Box 1)
  - CADAC Facility Agreements, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - DMHAS Capital Projects, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Clozapine, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Clozapine Responses, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Commission on Human Rights & Opportunities, 1986-1990 (Box 2)
  - Commissioner's Policy Statements, 1985-1990 (Box 2)
  - Commitment Statutes Committee, 1986-1990 (Box 2)
  - Comptroller's Office (Box 2)
  - Confidentiality, 1986-1989 (Box 2)
  - Conn. Alliance for the Mentally Ill, 1984-1990 (Box 2)
  - Conn. Council of Community MH Centers, 1986-1990 (Box 2)
  - Conn. Health Research & Info Systems Project, 1986-1988 (Box 2)
  - Connecticut Legal Rights Project, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Dept. of Children & Youth Services (Box 2)
  - Dept. of Correction, 1986-1989 (Box 2)
  - Deaf & Hearing Impaired, 1984-1988 (Box 2)
  - Dept. of Education (Box 2)
  - Dept. of Mental Health Mission Statement (Box 2)
  - Disabilities, 1987-1990 (Box 2)
  - Directory of Services (Box 3)
  - Dual Diagnosis, Mental Illness & Substance Abuse (Box 3)
  - Emergency Room Study, 1984-1986 (Box 3)
  - Ethics Commission, 1982-1990 (Box 3)
  - Forensic Services, 1976-1990 (Box 3)
  - Forensic Manuals, Conn. Valley Hospital, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Forensic Manuals, Fairfield Hills Hospital, 1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - Macro Report, Study of Forensic Services, 1984-1986 (Box 3)
  - Forensic Intermediate Treatment Unit (Box 3)
  - Gambling, 1981-1988 (Box 3)
  - Governing Body Minutes, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Governing Body Minutes, 1982-1989 (Box 4)
  - Governing Body Bylaws, 1973-1990 (Box 4)
  - Governor's Office, 1984-1990 (Box 4)
  - Governor's Task Force on Homelessness, 1985-1986 (Box 4)
  - Governor's Task Force on Nursing, 1987-1988 (Box 4)
  - State of CT Community Support Systems Strategy Development & Implementation Grant, 1988 (Box 4)
  - State of CT Community Support Systems Strategy, etc., 1985 (Box 4)
  - State of CT Community Support Systems Strategy, etc., 1984 (Box 4)
  - History, Dept. of Mental Health, Vol. I (Box 5)
  - History, Dept. of Mental Health, Vol. II (Box 5)
  - H.I.V. (Box 5)
  - Homeless Block Grant, 1988-1990 (Box 5)
  - Housing, 1988-1990 (Box 5)
  - Human Services Cabinet: AIDS, 1987-1988 (Box 5)
  - Human Services Cabinet, AIDS, 1988-1990 (Box 6)
  - Human Services Cabinet, 1982-1990 (Box 6)
  - Human Services Cabinet, Casey Initiative, 1988-1990 (Box 6)
  - Human Services Cabinet, Poverty, 1988-1990 (Box 6)
  - Human Services Cabinet, Regional Boundaries, 1988-1989 (Box 6)
  - DMHAS Info Systems Development, 1983-1990 (Box 6)
  - Institute of Living, 1988-1990 (Box 6)
  - Insurance: Blue Ribbon Commission, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Involuntary Medication, Right to Refuse Medication (Box 6)
  - J.C.A.H.O., 1985-1989 (Box 6)
  - Robert Wood Johnson Foundation, 1981-1989 (Box 6)
  - Legislative Correspondence (Box 6)
  - Legislative Program Review & Investigations Committee (Box 6)
  - Licensure, 1981-1987 (Box 6)
  - Long-Term Care, 1981-1990 (Box 6)
  - Media, 1990 (Box 7)
  - Medicaid, 1990 (Box 7)
  - Medicaid Mental Health Study, Correspondence, 1988 (Box 7)
  - Medicaid Mental Health Study, Reports, 1988 (Box 7)
  - Medication, 1984-1990 (Box 7)
  - Medication Errors, 1986-1987 (Box 7)
  - Mental Health Association, 1978-1990 (Box 7)
  - Mental Health Plan, 1989-1991 (Box 7)
  - Dept. of Mental Retardation, 1980-1983 (Box 7)
  - Dept. of Mental Retardation, 1984-1985 (Box 7)
  - Dept. of Mental Retardation, 1986-1988 (Box 7)
  - Dept. of Mental Retardation, 1989-1990 (Box 7)
  - DMR/DMH Interagency Agreement, 1984-1990 (Box 7)
  - Middletown Health Care Center, 1983-1990 (Box 8)
  - DMH Community Support System Program Development, 1985 (Box 8)
  - State Mental Health Plan, 1982-1988 (Box 8)
  - State Comprehensive Mental Health Plan, 1982-1989 (Box 8)
  - Narcotics Advisory Council Minutes, 1963-1967 (Box 8)
  - National Institute of Mental Health, 1986-1990 (Box 8)
  - Personnel, 1988-1990 (Box 8)
  - Protection & Advocacy, 1985-1990 (Box 8)
  - Plan for Closure of a State Mental Health Hospital, 1981 (Box 8)
  - Psychiatric Security Review Board, 1986-1990 (Box 8)
  - Quality Assurance, 1986-1993 (Box 9)
  - Quality Assurance Plan, 1982 (Box 9)
  - Quality Assurance: Case Management (Box 9)
  - Quality Assurance: Crisis Intervention (Box 9)
  - Quality Assurance: Mental Health Master Plan, 1985-1987 (Box 9)
  - Quality Assurance: Partial Hospital (Box 9)
  - Quality Assurance: Program Standards, 1986-1988 (Box 9)
  - Quality Assurance: Psycho-Social Rehab, 1985-1991 (Box 9)
  - Quality Assurance: Residential Services (Box 9)
  - Quality Assurance: Vocational Rehab (Box 9)
  - Quality of Work Life, 1984-1990 (Box 9)
  - Refugee Mental Health Treatment (Box 10)
  - Region I (Correspondence), 1990 (Box 10)
  - Region II, 1990 (Box 10)
  - Region III, 1990 (Box 10)
  - Regional Directors Meeting Minutes, 1986-1990 (Box 10)
  - Regional Mental Health Boards (Box 10)
  - Research: CSP Demonstration Project, 1990 (Box 10)
  - Restraint and Seclusion (Box 10)
  - Resuscitate (Do Not) Policy (Box 10)
  - Ribicoff Research Facilities, 1986 (Box 10)
  - Dept. of Social Services (Box 11)
  - Dept. of Mental Health Statistics, 1981-1990 (Box 11)
  - Stigma: The Impact of Community Education (Box 11)
  - Supported Employment, 1987-1990 (Box 11)
  - Tables of Organization (Box 11)
  - Task Force on AIDS (Box 11)
  - Task Force on Appointment of Conservators (Box 11)
  - Task Force on the Elderly (Box 11)
  - Task Force on Evolving Role of Physicians, 1987-1990 (Box 11)
  - Task Force: Governor's Blue Ribbon on Mental Health, 1983 (Box 11)
  - Task Force on Mental Illness, 1983 (Box 11)
  - Task Force: PA 89-325, Final Report (Box 11)
  - Task Force on Infection Control, 1988 (Box 11)
  - Task Force on Nursing Shortage (Box 12)
  - Task Force: Governor's Task Force on Traumatic Brain Injury, 1986-1987 (Box 12)
  - Task Force: Governor's to Study HMOs (Box 12)
  - Task Force on Veterans' Home (Box 12)
  - UCONN Psych Intensive Care Unit (Box 12)
  - UCONN Social Work Contract, 1987-1990 (Box 12)
  - Workers' Compensation (Box 12)
  - Yale University, 1977-1989 (Box 12)
  - Yale University, 1990-1992 (Box 12)
  - Facilities
    - Facilities Campus Plan Correspondence, 1984-1990 (Box 13)
    - Capitol Region Mental Health Center (Box 13)
    - Cedarcrest Hospital (Box 13)
    - Connecticut Mental Health Center (Box 13)
    - Connecticut Valley Hospital, 1990 (Box 13)
    - Connecticut Valley Hospital, 1983 (Box 13)
    - Connecticut Valley Hospital, 1972-1982 (Box 13)
    - CVH: Middletown Tragedy, Vol. I, 1989 (Box 13)
    - CVH: Middletown Tragedy, Vol. II, 1989 (Box 13)
    - CVH: Eddy Home, 1986-1988 (Box 13)
    - Greater Bridgeport Community Mental Health Center (Box 13)
  - Campus Plans
    - Campus Plan, Conn. Valley Hospital, 1988-1990 (Box 14)
    - Campus Plan, Dept. of Mental Health, 1987-1989 (Box 14)
    - Campus Plan, Dept. of Mental Health, 1989 (Box 14)
    - Campus Plan, Dept. of Mental Health, 1990 (Box 14)
    - Campus Plan, Fairfield Hills Hospital, 1990 (Box 14)
    - Campus Plan, Norwich Hospital, 1990 (Box 14)
  - Facilities
    - DuBois Center, 1988-1990 (Box 15)
    - Fairfield Hills Hospital, 1983-1990 (Box 15)
    - Norwich Hospital, 1986-1990 (Box 15)
    - Norwich Hospital, Register of Historic Places Whiting Forensic, 1987-1990 (Box 15)
    - Facility Advisory Boards, 1983-1989 (Box 15)
  - Reports
    - Report: Accomplishments in the Mental Health System, 1981-1986 (Box 16)
    - Dept. of Mental Health Annual Reports, 1966-1978 (Box 16)
    - Dept. of Mental Health Annual Reports, 1981-1990 (Box 16)
    - Assorted Facility Annual Reports, 1967-1975 (Box 16)
    - Report: Assertive Community Treatment Service, 1987 (Box 16)
    - Report: DMH Now, 1989-1990 (Box 16)
    - Macro Study on Alcohol Treatment, 1984 (Box 16)
    - DMH & DMR Final Report, 1990 (Box 16)
    - MEDICAID Report, 1988 (Box 16)
    - DMH Briefing Documents, 1989-1994 (Box 17)
    - REPORT: People with Prolonged Mental Illness, 1988 (Box 17)
    - Monthly Psych Inpatient Services Reports, 1987 (Box 17)
    - Monthly Psych Inpatient Services Reports, 1988 (Box 17)
    - Monthly Psych Inpatient Services Reports, 1989 (Box 17)
    - Reports on Staffing Needs, Admission to a Mental Hospital, Plan for Closure of State Mental Hospital in Connecticut, 1958-1981 (Box 17)
    - Torrey Report: Care of the Seriously Mentally Ill, 1990 (Box 17)
    - Torrey Report: Care of the Seriously Mentally Ill, 1988 (Box 17)
    - Whiting Forensic Macro Systems Report, 1986 (Box 17)
    - Alternative Models in MH Services Delivery (Dane County), 1989 (Box 17)